<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OPSEC | Hacker OPSEC]]></title>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/categories/opsec/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-09T21:31:28+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://grugq.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[the grugq]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[the.grugq@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jihadist Fan Crypto]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/08/09/jihadist-fan-crypto/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T20:41:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/08/09/jihadist-fan-crypto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Think of <em>Mujahideen Secrets</em> as a branded promotional tool, sort of
like if Manchester United released a branded fan chat app.</p>

<p>Although there has been a lot of FUD written about the encrypted messaging systems
developed and promoted by jihadis groups, very little has focused on the how
they are actually used. I wrote <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/93584051363/how-al-qaeda-uses-encryption-post-snowden-part-2">some notes about this earlier</a>
but wanted to expand on the subject in more depth.</p>

<h2>Web Warriors: Security Practices on Jihadi Web Forums</h2>

<p>There are a number of internet web forums that are used by supporters of the various
jihadi groups fighting in the middle east. These sites are primarily cheerleading
and "in grouping" social networks, rather than opertational message boards.</p>

<p>An important point to understand about these online forums is that they are about
group dynamics. They provide a mechanism for people to feel like they are part
of the struggle with a graded scale of committment. They dont actually need
to worry about getting their hands dirty or risking their lives (technically, they might be risking their lives and freedom).</p>

<p>The sites all attempt to educate their users on security best practices, for example
the Islamic State (nee ISIS) web forum heavily <a href="https://twitter.com/switch_d/status/484806826404618241/photo/1">promotes the use of TAILS</a>, AQAP <a href="https://twitter.com/switch_d/status/484809802363969538">advocates for Tor usage in a 9 page guide</a>. Despite
this, few users actually bother with security precautions. Indeed, many continue
to use Facebook and Skype as their <a href="https://twitter.com/Raed667/status/495791460915347456">primary communications channels</a> with fellow
online jihadists.</p>

<p>The encryption tools are branded software for self identifying
jihadis to <a href="https://twitter.com/Raed667/status/495791831721213952">feel like they belong</a>.
Indeed, other than the <a href="https://twitter.com/switch_d/status/495908728500404224">media outlets</a> who
emphasise the use of the tools (branding and messaging), the actual jihadis have
a hard time using the tools. Actual web jihadis <a href="https://twitter.com/switch_d/status/495909042490191872">complain of usability problems</a>
that prevent them from using the tools.</p>

<p>The media outlets for the different groups: IS, Nusra, AQ, all make sure that
their followers know about their own branded encrypted messenger. Indeed, this
is the primary clue to how these apps are actually used. They are branding tools
that promote in-group sentiment. "I'm using the AQ encrypted messenger, so I am
basically AQ". These tools deliberately identify the user as a jihadi associate,
not by accident or due to bad security practice, but rather as a deliberate part
of their value proposition. "Use our encrypted messaging app and you will securely
let the world know that you are with us!"</p>

<p>All of the major apps are simply branded wrappers around industry standard
libraries, ciphers, and protocols. There is nothing particularly Islamic or
Jihadist about them except the branding. That is because <strong>the branding is actually the point</strong>.
These are just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_theory">social signals</a>.
Using AQAP's messaging tool is the rough equivalent of wearing a sports jersey.
It signals to others that there is group identity. (Of course, given the outlaw
nature of these groups it seems like an extremely poor life decision)</p>

<p>These apps are not designed for actual clandestine operational use. They are for
making a social statement. Signaling membership in a peer group. Despite this
simple purpose for using the apps, there is still remarkably low uptake amongst
the online jihadist set who still primarily rely on Facebook and Skype for comms.</p>

<p>So if almost no one is using the encryption apps, and those that do are using them
to signal membership in a broader organisation, what are the real jihadis using
operationally? <strong>Facebook</strong>.</p>

<h2>Jihadi Operational Covert Communications:</h2>

<p>There was a Facebook account <a href="https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100004481327363&amp;fref=ufi">"sniper outside the law"</a> that was posting clear text, but coded, messages
believed to be related to jihadi operations in Tunisia. The account has been taken
down and the guy running it <a href="https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=ar&amp;tl=en&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.shemsfm.net%2Far%2Factualite%2F%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A8%D8%B6-%D8%B9%D9%84%D9%89-%D8%B5%D8%A7%D8%AD%D8%A8-%D8%B5%D9%81%D8%AD%D8%A9-%D9%82%D9%86%D8%A7%D8%B5-%D8%AE%D8%A7%D8%B1%D8%AC-%D8%B9%D9%86-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D9%86%D9%88%D9%86-87983">was arrested</a>.</p>

<p>Here are some examples of what he was posting (<a href="http://pastebin.com/hT0DJT05">taken from here</a>):</p>

<p><code>
Eagle 1 group please change route to k :?via trees !.ch
</code></p>

<p><code>
Refiling will be through the loaded mule same place of refiling thank you
</code></p>

<p><code>
(Yesterdays posts (before today's attack))
To all "units" please change direction towards .?k1 after 500m (meters?). Info came from scout about invaluable avant-post
</code></p>

<p><code>
https://www.facebook.com/permalink.php?story_fbid=325792687580106&amp;id=100004481327363
Expecting news in the coming days we promise heavy news(important), For those fighting Islam? wake up before it is too late you traitors and snitches you will regret your tyranny
</code></p>

<h2>Jihadi Encryption Is Overrated</h2>

<p>The key take away is that the encrypted messaging apps from ISIS or AQAP are as
operationaly relevant as an encrypted messaging app from Man U or Liverpool. It
might be exciting for some hardcore fans who want to show their support, but the
real players don't touch the stuff.</p>

<p>Real jihadis use <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/68453478391/secure-communications">secure codes</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jun/15/iraq-isis-arrest-jihadists-wealth-power">couriers</a>, not some Android toy My First Crypto Chat.</p>

<p><strong>Must Read</strong>: <a href="http://krypt3ia.wordpress.com/2014/08/09/post-hoc-ergo-propter-hoc-poop-recorded-future-and-the-jihadi-fud-o-sphere/">An article by Kryt3ia</a> (published minutes before me, the swine!)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When In Doubt, It's A Tout]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/06/16/when-in-doubt-its-a-tout/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T00:25:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/06/16/when-in-doubt-its-a-tout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>When in doubt, it's a tout</h1>

<h2>Robust Operational Security Practices Aren't Enough</h2>

<p>A British man, Lauri Love, has been <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2014/02/28/lauri_love_us_federal_reserve_hacking_charges/">indicted for hacking</a>. The indictment
is thin on details, but does have some interesting OPSEC insights that can be teased out by the patient reader.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.justice.gov/usao/nj/Press/files/pdffiles/2013/Love,%20Lauri%20Indictment.pdf">indictment of Lauri Love</a> doesn't reveal much about how he was identified. There is some interesting info about the operational security measures taken by his crew, and they appear robust. The lack of information on how Mr Love was caught, along with the revelation of good security practices suggests one thing: informant.</p>

<p>This post will only highlight the good operational security practices of the hacker group, since we don't know what the mistakes were.</p>

<h2>Indictment Critical Analysis</h2>

<p>The indictment lists four members of the crew:</p>

<ol>
<li>Lauri Love, "nsh", "peace", "route"</li>
<li>CC-1 "in New South Wales, Australia"</li>
<li>CC-2 "in Australia"</li>
<li>CC-3 "in Sweden"</li>
</ol>


<p>If I were to venture a guess, I'd reckon that <em>CC-1</em> was caught first and became the informant used to take down the crew. I think this because <em>CC-1</em> has the most specific geographic information, and the others are more vague in their location. As if there was a lot of effort invested in locating <em>CC-1</em>, and then the investigation focussed in on Mr Love.</p>

<h2>Timeline</h2>

<ul>
<li>October, 2012: Start of the conspiracy</li>
<li>October 2, 2012: Army Network Enterprise Technology Command ("NETCOM") hack</li>
<li>October 6, 2012: log of <code>nsh</code> on IRC discussing NETCOM hack with <em>CC-1</em>, later w/ <em>CC-2</em></li>
<li>October 7-8, 2012: Army Contracting Command's Army Materiel Command ("ACC") SQLI hack</li>
<li><p>October 10, 2012: LOVE discusses ACC hack on IRC</p></li>
<li><p>October, 2013: End of the conspiracy</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Hacking 101</h2>

<p>The crew used scanners to locate vulnerable servers to exploit, and they shared the findings via their IRC.</p>

<pre><code>peace: so can pivot and scan for other vulns [vulnerabilities] 
peace: we might be able to get at real confidential shit
</code></pre>

<p>The crew used SQLI and ColdFusion exploits.</p>

<p>The crew used proxies and <code>Tor</code> to mask the origins of their attacks.</p>

<blockquote><p>conceal their attacks by disguising, through the use of Proxy Servers, the IP addresses from which their attacks originated. Defendant LOVE and the other Co-Conspirators further used the Tor network, which was an anonymizing proxy service, to hide their activities.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Operational Security Measures</h2>

<h3>Migration</h3>

<p>The crew moved comms to new systems <strong>and</strong> changed their identities when they did so. This is a very good practice. Unfortunately, it appears that at least one member was logging the comms traffic. This created a security problem that could be exploited
by the authorities.</p>

<pre><code>route: consideration 1 : behaviour profile should not change 
route: public side i mean 
route: so whatever "normal", activities we do 
route: should continue 
route: but we move from this irc to better system 
route: also 
route: these nicks should change 
route: i think 
route: when we get on new communications 
route: all new names
</code></pre>

<p><strong>OPSEC Violation</strong>: No logs, no crime. Do not keep any unnecessary logs. If
there is operationally critical information, make a record of that information.
Practically, this means: cut and paste into a file; keep that file encrypted.</p>

<p><strong>OPSEC Lesson</strong>: Migrating communications infrastructure and changing identities
regularly is a good idea. It creates chronologically compartmented silos of info
that limit the impact of a compromise. It can provide plausible deniability,
and it can reduce the severity of a compromise. Do not contaminate between the
compartments. And, of course, ensure that each commo channel is secure.</p>

<h3>Logistical Compartmentation</h3>

<p>For at least some operations (all?) the crew spun up a new dedicated support
server. This compartmented server was then discarded after use to minimize the
connection to the group and any other operations. This is very effective OPSEC.</p>

<pre><code>CC#2: but server must have no link to you or us
peace: :)
CC#2: when done we kill it
CC#2: for this plan
CC#2: we can reopen another one for other ongoing stuff
CC#2: but once this plan done we need to make sure they cannot all trace it back to us
</code></pre>

<p><strong>OPSEC Lesson</strong>: Compartment as much as possible for each operation to avoid
linking separate ops together. This also helps contain the damage if an operation
is compromised and an investigation launched. Dedicated logistical infrastructure
is best. Don't forget to santize it, both at the beginning and the end of the op.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Even a group with robust operational security practices is vulnerable to the oldest
trick in the book: the informant. The take away lessons are slightly more interesting:</p>

<ul>
<li>Migrate comms and identity on a regular basis</li>
<li>Never store incriminating logs</li>
<li>Compartment heavily, and sanitize frequently</li>
</ul>


<p>So it is sad news for Mr Lauri Love facing hacking charges, but at least there're
some valuable OPSEC lessons for the rest of us. Remember: No logs, no crime.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York's Finest OPSEC]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/13/new-yorks-finest-opsec/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T19:35:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/13/new-yorks-finest-opsec</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>NYPD Social Media Investigation OPSEC</h2>

<p>The NYPD created an operations formula for conducting undercover investigations on social media. The <a href="http://publicintelligence.net/nypd-social-network-investigations/">procedural document</a> reveals the operational security for these investigations. The security is founded on the use of an "online alias" (the officer's undercover account) and strict compartmentation. Given the capabilities of the adversaries that the NYPD faces this is probably sufficient security.</p>

<p>It is a fascinating glimpse into the operational process of an investigation. Definitely worth reading to get a sense of what the police face when conducting an online investigation (hint: paperwork).</p>

<h2>Core NYPD OPSEC</h2>

<p>Fundamentally this is basic operational security grounded on compartmentation. The use of dedicated hardware, and pseudononymous internet access, allows the officer to create and operate an online undercover account without any links to the NYPD. The basic security precautions are designed to protect the officer's laptop from being compromised. A compromised laptop could enable the adversary to conduct a counterintelligence investigation.</p>

<ul>
<li>Compartmentation:

<ul>
<li>Use dedicated hardward and pseudononymous internet connection (laptop + "aircard")</li>
<li>Avoid accounts, usernames, passwords associated with NYPD</li>
<li>Avoid personal accounts and internet access</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Basic Computer Security:

<ul>
<li>Delete "spam"</li>
<li>Don't open attachments</li>
<li>Exercise caution when clicking on links</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>This is very basic stuff, but should be more than sufficient against the adversaries that the NYPD pursues. These adversaries should not have access to any of the records of the phone company supplying the internet access.</p>

<h2>Primary Document</h2>

<p>Here is the information that is required to create the undercover account:</p>

<blockquote><ol type="a">
<li> Username (online alias)</li>
<li> Identifiers and pedigree to be utilized for the online alias, such as email address, username and date of birth.</li>
<li> Do not include password(s) for online alias and ensure password(s) are secured at all times.</li>
<li> Indicate whether there is a need to requisition a Department laptop with aircard.</li>
<li>Review photograph to be used in conjunction with online alias, if applicable.</li>
<li> Consider the purpose for which the photograph is being used and the source of the photograph.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is the full section dealing with operational security:</p>

<blockquote><h1>Operational Considerations</h1>

<p>When a member of the service accesses any social media site using a Department network connection, there is a risk that the Department can be identified as the user of the social media. Given this possibility of identification during an investigation, members of the service should be aware that Department issued laptops with aircards have been configured to avoid detection and are available from the Management Information Systems Division (MISD). A confidential Internet connection (e.g., Department laptop with aircard) will aid in maintaining confidentiality during an investigation. Members who require a laptop with aircard to complete the investigation shall contact MISD Help Desk, upon APPROVAL of investigation, and provide required information.</p>

<p>In addition to using a Department laptop with aircard, members of the service are urged to take the following precautionary measures:</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>Avoid the use of a username or password that can be traced back to the member of the service or the Department;</li>
<li>Exercise caution when clicking on links in tweets, posts, and online advertisements;</li>
<li>Delete “spam” email without opening the email; and</li>
<li>Never open attachments to email unless the sender is known to the member of the service.</li>
</ol>


<p>Furthermore, recognizing the ease with which information can be gathered from minimal effort from an Internet search, the Department advises members against the use of personal, family, or other non-Department Internet accounts or ISP access for Department business. Such access creates the possibility that the member’s identity may be exposed to others through simple search and counter-surveillance techniques.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Undercover operations online rely on very basic operational security. Primarily compartmentation and reviews to ensure that the account isn't going to be associated with the NYPD.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Fistful of Surveillance]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/10/a-fistful-of-surveillance/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T19:11:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/10/a-fistful-of-surveillance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The publication of <a href="https://firstlook.org/theintercept/article/2014/02/10/the-nsas-secret-role/">this piece</a> at <a href="https://firstlook.org/theintercept/">The Intercept</a> about NSA targeting via mobile phones prompted me to release this collection of notes. Some quotes and statements in the article wrongly promote the idea that the SIM card is the only unique identifier in a mobile phone. I've enumerated the identifiers that exist, and they go far beyond the SIM card. At a minimum the physical identifiers of a mobile phone are the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_mobile_subscriber_identity">IMSI</a> and the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Mobile_Station_Equipment_Identity">IMEI</a>, that is the SIM card and the mobile phone hardware itself.</p>

<p>This is a short collection of notes I've put together on how you can be identified via your mobile phone. If you want to securely use a mobile phone, you'll need to use a burner. This is non-trivial. <a href="http://b3rn3d.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/01/22/burner-phone-best-practices/">Here's a good guide</a>.</p>

<h2>Clandestine Mobile Phone Use</h2>

<p>Mobile phones should primarily be used for signalling, rather than for actually communicating operational information. Remember the golden rule of telephone conversations:</p>

<ul>
<li>keep it short</li>
<li>keep it simple</li>
<li>stick to your cover</li>
</ul>


<h2>Identifiers</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Location</strong>

<ul>
<li>Specific location (home, place of work, etc.)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nature.com/srep/2013/130325/srep01376/full/srep01376.html">Mobility pattern</a> (from home, via commuter route, to work) -- very unique, 4 loc's will identify 90%</li>
<li>Paired mobility pattern with a known device (known as "mirroring", when two devices or more devices travel together)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Network</strong>

<ul>
<li>numbers dialed (who you call)</li>
<li>calls received (who calls you)</li>
<li>calling pattern (numbers dialed, for how long, how frequently)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Physical</strong>

<ul>
<li>IMEI (mobile phone device ID)</li>
<li>IMSI (mobile phone telco subscriber ID)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Content</strong>

<ul>
<li>Identifiers, e.g. names, locations</li>
<li>Voice fingerprinting</li>
<li>Keywords</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Mitigations</h2>

<h3>Turn it OFF, for real.</h3>

<p>Know how to turn the phone to a completely off state. This means removing the battery, taking out the SIM card and placing in a shielded bag (if possible). This <strong>really off</strong> state is how you store and transport the phone when not in use.</p>

<p>A note on storage: it should not be at your house or anywhere that is directly linked to you.</p>

<h3>Take a hike, buster</h3>

<p>Where you use the phone is itself very important. Never use it at locations which are associated with you, that means never at home, never at the office/work, never at a friend's house. Never have the phone in an <strong>ON</strong> state at locations that are associated with you, or your immediate social network. Never.</p>

<p>Do not turn the phone in the same location as a phone associated with you. Make sure that your real phone is somewhere else, but not in an <strong>OFF</strong> state if possible. You don't want the disappearance of one phone from the network to coincide with the appearance of another. Paired events are indicators of relation, and you want to avoid those as much as possible. You also want you regular phone to appear with a typical usage pattern, which means keeping it on as you normally would.</p>

<h3>Contamination, avoid it</h3>

<p>Never use different phones from the same location.</p>

<p>Never carry phones for different compartments together (keep them turned off, batteries out)</p>

<p>Never carry phones turned on over the same routes you normally take. Avoid patterns and predictability.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Codes, What Are They Good For?]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/12/21/codes-what-are-they-good-for/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T20:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/12/21/codes-what-are-they-good-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What is a Secure Communication?</h2>

<p>The goals of secure communications are the following. Some of these are surprisingly difficult to achieve:</p>

<ol>
<li>Make the <strong>content</strong> of a message <strong>unreadable</strong> to parties other than the intended one(s)</li>
<li>Make the <strong>meaning</strong> of a message <strong>inaccessible</strong> to parties other than the intended one(s)</li>
<li>Avoid <strong>traffic analysis</strong> — don’t let other parties know that a connection exists between the communicating parties</li>
<li>Avoid <strong>knowledge of the communication</strong> — don’t let other parties know the communication channel or pathway exists</li>
</ol>


<p>The first and second objectives can be accomplished using some combination of <strong>cryptography</strong> and <strong>coding</strong>. Unfortunately, this is the easy part. The more
complicated and difficult component of a secure communications infrastructure is
achieving the third and fourth objectives. For now, however, I will focus only
on the first two issues: protecting content, and meaning.</p>

<p>First lets define our terms so we can discuss the subject with clarity:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Cryptography</strong> systems that use transformation processes to turn <em>signal into noise</em>, by obscuring the symbols used for communication</li>
<li><strong>Coding</strong> systems that substitute or alter meaning, and thus hide the real message</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Eagle Has Landed</h2>

<p>Codes are extremely useful mechanisms for sending small messages, although as they are <em>plain text</em> their hidden mean can be revealed once the <em>key</em> is cracked. Another issue with codes is that they are inflexible, compared to a cipher system. Coding requires pre-arranged mappings of meanings (what symbols or words translate to what), or at least pre-arranged mechanisms to derive the mappings (e.g., book codes).</p>

<p>To be effective, a code must maintain <strong>proper grammar</strong>, be <strong>consistent</strong>, and fit a <strong>plausible</strong> pretext. If it fits these requirements, and is used appropriately (briefly, consistently, with <a href="http://www.stratfor.com/weekly/20100616_watching_watchers"><em>cover for action</em></a>) then a code system is an excellent choice for simple signalling purposes.</p>

<h3>Doing It Right</h3>

<p>During World War II the BBC cooperated with the intelligence services to send
open code signals to operatives in the occupied territories. These signals were
prearranged with the operatives, and then sent out at two scheduled times. This
signalling channel was used exclusively for indicating whether an operation was
going to take place.</p>

<p>The BBC would broadcast the signal for the first time at 1930, and then confirm
the signal at 2115. If the operation had been canceled before the second scheduled
signal window, the code phrase would not be repeated.</p>

<p>During the early phase of the war, the code system was slightly more complex.
There would be a positive code, and a negative code, for example: "Jeanne sends
her greetings" might be a "go code", and "Jeanne says hello" might be the "abort
code". Later this was simplified to just the positive code (a tradition that,
apparently, the CIA still follows).</p>

<h3>Doing It Wrong</h3>

<p>There are problems when codes are used inconsistently. For example, some <a href="http://www.wmob.com/cast.html">mafia codes</a> used oblique references to the boss as "aunt", or "Aunt Julia". This was very ineffective when the mafioso suffered pronoun slippage and called their "aunt" "he".</p>

<ul>
<li>"Ah, Aunt Julia said he wanted to help me out, too."</li>
</ul>


<h2>Codes Gone Wild</h2>

<p>I've collected some examples of <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/60890158036/al-qaedas-codes">real al Qaida codes</a> that were used actively used
prior to the 9/11 attacks. Other types of basic open code are "business code",
which is also used by some criminal groups, where the actors are refered to as
business interests or rivals, and criminal activities are described as "projects"
or other innocuous business terms.</p>

<p>A simple code that was used by two KGB operatives was the phrase "I think we
should go fishing now", which indicated that they should discuss business.</p>

<h3>KGB Says What?</h3>

<p>During the early stages of the KGB handling of their FBI penetration Hanssen,
they had a mishap with locating and loading the deaddrop for his payment. To
correct this error, they had to contact Hanssen by phone and use a code that was
not pre-arranged (there was no contingency in place for "what happens if we cant
find the dead drop"). The dead drop location was underneath a footbridge and the
KGB operative had placed his load underneath the wrong corner.</p>

<p>Since they had used a pretext of purchasing a used car for
their initial contact, the KGB continued to use that pretext for their "oops!"
communique. The KGB operative prepared his telephone conversation
thoroughly before hand so that it would sound natural and plausible:</p>

<blockquote><p>KGB: The car is still available for you as we have agreed last time, I prepared
all the papers and left them on the same table. You didn't find them because I
put them in another corner of the table.</p>

<p>Hanssen: I see</p>

<p>KGB: You shouldn't worry, everything is okay. The papers are with me now.</p>

<p>Hanssen: Good</p>

<p>KGB: I believe under these circumstances, its not necessary to make any changes
concerning the place and time. Our company is reliable, and we are ready to
give you a substantial discount which will be enclosed in the papers. Now,
about the date of our meeting. I suggest that our meeting will take place
without delay on Febuary 13, one, three, 1:00 PM. Okay? Feburary 13</p>

<p>Hanssen: .... Okay.</p></blockquote>

<p>The conversations is clearly stilted and strange, but no so strange as to draw
attention to itself. It also doesn't reveal anything of the <strong>meaning</strong> that is
being relayed.</p>

<h3>Signaling Codes</h3>

<p>When creating a signaling code, it is important that the pretext for the signal
be broad and widely applicable. Generally it is better that the code be a
specific subject, rather than a specific phrase. Phrases are easy to mixup,
forget, or otherwise confuse. They are also more rigid and hard to work into
a conversation. A subject, on the other hand, is very easy to raise and discuss
in a plausible fashion without seeming forced or unnatural.</p>

<p>A final short code example. This is a signaling code, adapted from a novel,
however it accurately conveys how simple these codes can be. This is phone call
between two colleagues, where <em>Alice</em> has to signal an emergency has occured:</p>

<blockquote><p>Alice: Hi, sorry to call so late</p>

<p>Bob: No problem</p>

<p>Alice: Is our meeting scheduled for tomorrow at 8:30, or at 9?</p>

<p>Bob: It is 8:30, bright and early.</p>

<p>Alice: Ok, right. Just checking. Thanks, bye</p></blockquote>

<h2>Open Codes Fail Open</h2>

<p>When using a code to refer to a classified subject, even though unclassified terms
are used, the subject is still classified. This is a breach of security. See
the US Army <a href="http://www.ncms-isp.org/documents/COMSEC_Material.pdf">handbook on COMSEC</a>
section dealing with <em>ATTEMPTS TO DISGUISE INFORMATION</em> (Section 8.4).</p>

<blockquote><p>“Talking around” is a
technique in which you try to get the information across to the recipient in a
manner you believe will protect it. However, no matter how much you try to
change words about a classified or sensitive subject, it is still classified or
sensitive.</p>

<p>self-made reference system. This is an
attempt to encipher your conversation by using your own system. This system
rarely works because few people are clever enough to refer to an item of
information without actually revealing names, subjects, or other pertinent
information that would reveal the classified or sensitive meaning</p></blockquote>

<p>These are concerns to keep in mind when developing a code system for discussing
sensitive information.</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Codes: keep them generic, keep them consistent, limit their use to simple signalling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
