<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: intelligence | Hacker OPSEC]]></title>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/categories/intelligence/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-28T07:51:10+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://grugq.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[the grugq]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[the.grugq@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Win at Kung Fu and Hacking]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/22/challenges-for-hackers/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-22T20:02:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/22/challenges-for-hackers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Everybody Was Hack Foo Fighting</h2>

<p>I'm going to discuss a serious problem with the organisational structure and
social dynamics of the hacker community, and why this puts hackers at risk.
Hackers operate essentially the same way as the henchmen in a kung fu movie:
they attack the adversary one by one by one... always losing. This is a terrible
way of developing a robust core of knowledge about which OPSEC techniques work,
which techniques fail, and why.</p>

<h2>Organisational Learning for Dummies</h2>

<p>There are two types of knowledge: individual, and organisational. Hackers are
very individualistic, and the knowledge they acquire tends to be very
practical; experience based. There are few hacker organisations that seek to
collect, retain, test and spread knowledge. The organistations that do crop up
are either some zines, which are knowledge artefacts that transmit techne, or
hacker groups, which share tool chains and experience. However, these hacker
groups have very short lifespans (measured in months and single digit years,
not decades). They are compartmented in that there is some effort made to
retain the group's proprietary information, but internally they usually
have a very poor security posture. They are social groups in many ways, so
they are heavily compromised. As we say in infosec "crunchy on the outside,
chewy in the middle".</p>

<p>Their opposition, the intelligence agencies and law enforcement departments,
have decades of organisational history and knowledge. The individual members
can display wide ranges of skill and competence, but the resources and core
knowledge of the organisation dwarf what any individual hacker has available.
Many of the skills that a hacker needs to learn, his clandestine tradecraft
and OPSEC, are the sort of skills that organisations are excellent at
developing and disseminating. These are not very good skillsets for an
individual to learn through trial and error, because those errors have
significant negative consequences. An organisation can afford to lose people
as it learns how to deal with the adversary; an individual cannot afford to
make a similar sacrifice -- afterall, who would benefit from your negative
example?</p>

<h2>Challenges? More Like Opportunities!</h2>

<p>Hackers are facing some very serious challenges now:</p>

<ul>
<li>they lack organistations for collecting intelligence and knowledge about their adversary;</li>
<li>they face off against the adversary one at a time,</li>
<li>they learn very poorly from prior mistakes</li>
<li>they don't even know what skills they need,</li>
<li>and perhaps most dangerously, they aren't even aware they're in the game</li>
</ul>


<p>It is amusing how many people think that interrogations involve violence and
torture. Successful elicitation far more frequently involves whiskey,
flattery, playing dumb, and being doubtful ("<em>really? I didn't know it was
possible to do that. You must be pretty damn smart to have figured it
out...</em>").</p>

<h2>Winning at Secrets</h2>

<p>There needs to be more information available on the techniques used during
investigations, as well as before they begin. There needs to be documentation
on how to evade those techniques, and why those evasions are successful. That
knowledge needs to be captured and dissemminated out to those who can use it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
