<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: counterintelligence | Hacker OPSEC]]></title>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/categories/counterintelligence/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-13T19:42:16+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://grugq.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[the grugq]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[the.grugq@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York's Finest OPSEC]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/13/new-yorks-finest-opsec/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T19:35:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2014/02/13/new-yorks-finest-opsec</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>NYPD Social Media Investigation OPSEC</h2>

<p>The NYPD created an operations formula for conducting undercover investigations on social media. The <a href="http://publicintelligence.net/nypd-social-network-investigations/">procedural document</a> reveals the operational security for these investigations. The security is founded on the use of an "online alias" (the officer's undercover account) and strict compartmentation. Given the capabilities of the adversaries that the NYPD faces this is probably sufficient security.</p>

<p>It is a fascinating glimpse into the operational process of an investigation. Definitely worth reading to get a sense of what the police face when conducting an online investigation (hint: paperwork).</p>

<h2>Core NYPD OPSEC</h2>

<p>Fundamentally this is basic operational security grounded on compartmentation. The use of dedicated hardware, and pseudononymous internet access, allows the officer to create and operate an online undercover account without any links to the NYPD. The basic security precautions are designed to protect the officer's laptop from being compromised. A compromised laptop could enable the adversary to conduct a counterintelligence investigation.</p>

<ul>
<li>Compartmentation:

<ul>
<li>Use dedicated hardward and pseudononymous internet connection (laptop + "aircard")</li>
<li>Avoid accounts, usernames, passwords associated with NYPD</li>
<li>Avoid personal accounts and internet access</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Basic Computer Security:

<ul>
<li>Delete "spam"</li>
<li>Don't open attachments</li>
<li>Exercise caution when clicking on links</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>This is very basic stuff, but should be more than sufficient against the adversaries that the NYPD pursues. These adversaries should not have access to any of the records of the phone company supplying the internet access.</p>

<h2>Primary Document</h2>

<p>Here is the information that is required to create the undercover account:</p>

<blockquote><ol type="a">
<li> Username (online alias)</li>
<li> Identifiers and pedigree to be utilized for the online alias, such as email address, username and date of birth.</li>
<li> Do not include password(s) for online alias and ensure password(s) are secured at all times.</li>
<li> Indicate whether there is a need to requisition a Department laptop with aircard.</li>
<li>Review photograph to be used in conjunction with online alias, if applicable.</li>
<li> Consider the purpose for which the photograph is being used and the source of the photograph.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is the full section dealing with operational security:</p>

<blockquote><h2>Operational Considerations</h2>

<p>When a member of the service accesses any social media site using a Department network connection, there is a risk that the Department can be identified as the user of the social media. Given this possibility of identification during an investigation, members of the service should be aware that Department issued laptops with aircards have been configured to avoid detection and are available from the Management Information Systems Division (MISD). A confidential Internet connection (e.g., Department laptop with aircard) will aid in maintaining confidentiality during an investigation. Members who require a laptop with aircard to complete the investigation shall contact MISD Help Desk, upon APPROVAL of investigation, and provide required information.</p>

<p>In addition to using a Department laptop with aircard, members of the service are urged to take the following precautionary measures:</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>Avoid the use of a username or password that can be traced back to the member of the service or the Department;</li>
<li>Exercise caution when clicking on links in tweets, posts, and online advertisements;</li>
<li>Delete “spam” email without opening the email; and</li>
<li>Never open attachments to email unless the sender is known to the member of the service.</li>
</ol>


<p>Furthermore, recognizing the ease with which information can be gathered from minimal effort from an Internet search, the Department advises members against the use of personal, family, or other non-Department Internet accounts or ISP access for Department business. Such access creates the possibility that the member’s identity may be exposed to others through simple search and counter-surveillance techniques.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Undercover operations online rely on very basic operational security. Primarily compartmentation and reviews to ensure that the account isn't going to be associated with the NYPD.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Win at Kung Fu and Hacking]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/22/challenges-for-hackers/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-22T20:02:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/22/challenges-for-hackers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Everybody Was Hack Foo Fighting</h2>

<p>I'm going to discuss a serious problem with the organisational structure and
social dynamics of the hacker community, and why this puts hackers at risk.
Hackers operate essentially the same way as the henchmen in a kung fu movie:
they attack the adversary one by one by one... always losing. This is a terrible
way of developing a robust core of knowledge about which OPSEC techniques work,
which techniques fail, and why.</p>

<h2>Organisational Learning for Dummies</h2>

<p>There are two types of knowledge: individual, and organisational. Hackers are
very individualistic, and the knowledge they acquire tends to be very
practical; experience based. There are few hacker organisations that seek to
collect, retain, test and spread knowledge. The organistations that do crop up
are either some zines, which are knowledge artefacts that transmit techne, or
hacker groups, which share tool chains and experience. However, these hacker
groups have very short lifespans (measured in months and single digit years,
not decades). They are compartmented in that there is some effort made to
retain the group's proprietary information, but internally they usually
have a very poor security posture. They are social groups in many ways, so
they are heavily compromised. As we say in infosec "crunchy on the outside,
chewy in the middle".</p>

<p>Their opposition, the intelligence agencies and law enforcement departments,
have decades of organisational history and knowledge. The individual members
can display wide ranges of skill and competence, but the resources and core
knowledge of the organisation dwarf what any individual hacker has available.
Many of the skills that a hacker needs to learn, his clandestine tradecraft
and OPSEC, are the sort of skills that organisations are excellent at
developing and disseminating. These are not very good skillsets for an
individual to learn through trial and error, because those errors have
significant negative consequences. An organisation can afford to lose people
as it learns how to deal with the adversary; an individual cannot afford to
make a similar sacrifice -- afterall, who would benefit from your negative
example?</p>

<h2>Challenges? More Like Opportunities!</h2>

<p>Hackers are facing some very serious challenges now:</p>

<ul>
<li>they lack organistations for collecting intelligence and knowledge about their adversary;</li>
<li>they face off against the adversary one at a time,</li>
<li>they learn very poorly from prior mistakes</li>
<li>they don't even know what skills they need,</li>
<li>and perhaps most dangerously, they aren't even aware they're in the game</li>
</ul>


<p>It is amusing how many people think that interrogations involve violence and
torture. Successful elicitation far more frequently involves whiskey,
flattery, playing dumb, and being doubtful ("<em>really? I didn't know it was
possible to do that. You must be pretty damn smart to have figured it
out...</em>").</p>

<h2>Winning at Secrets</h2>

<p>There needs to be more information available on the techniques used during
investigations, as well as before they begin. There needs to be documentation
on how to evade those techniques, and why those evasions are successful. That
knowledge needs to be captured and dissemminated out to those who can use it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[required reading]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/06/required-reading/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-06T07:23:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/11/06/required-reading</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a short list of articles and papers that you absolutely must read if you want to understand OPSEC.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/bitstream/handle/10822/553096/mobleyBlake.pdf?sequence=1">Terrorist Group Counterintelligence</a> :: This is the thesis which later became the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Terrorism-Counterintelligence-Terrorist-Detection-Irregular/dp/0231158769">Terrorism and Counterintelligence</a>. Read at least one of them (the thesis is free).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.oss.net/dynamaster/file_archive/100102/0a947a77d762061cc87ec541c2d2dcc7/2010-01-02%20Dulles%20on%20Tradecraft%20via%20Srodes.pdf">Allen Dulles's 73 Rules of Spycraft</a> :: This is the handbook of how to live and operate securely. It is 50 years old and it has aged remarkably well. Read it. Study it. This will be on the test.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA505161">Clandestine Cellular Networks</a> :: This paper deals primarily with the lessons learned from fighting insurgents, but it is extremely valuable as a handbook on tradecraft. I previously posted just the tradecraft <a href="http://grugq.github.io/resources/tradecraft-howto.pdf">chapter</a> for people who don't want to slog through all of it. I suggest reading all of it.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://igcc3.ucsd.edu/research/security/DACOR/presentations/Shapiro.pdf">The Terrorists Challenge: Security, Efficiency, Control</a> :: This paper examines the primary trade offs that need to be made when operating a covert organisation. If you have multiple people working in secret, managing them and their work requires making tradeoffs between security, efficiency and control. This paper will help you to understand those tradeoffs.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Optional</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/10576100802670803">A Study of al Quaeda's use of Intelligence and Counterintelligence</a> :: This pulls a lot of the information above into a single case study of a covert (terrorist) organisation planning and conducting an operation. Anything else you can lay your hands on by the author I recommend as well.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Silk Road Security]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/silk-road-security/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T18:53:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/silk-road-security</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Counterintelligence Lessons for Drug Dealers</h2>

<p><strong>NOTE</strong> Events have overtaken my slow writing speed. This post was in the works
before the Silk Road bust in September 2013. I'm uploading it anyway because it
has some useful information, however there seems little point in finish it now.</p>

<p>The dealers on Silk Road ship a large amount of illegal products around the world, and it is clear that they're successful at it. However, the US Postal service has been aware that drug dealers user their service for shipping illegal substances and has developed guidelines for determining suspect packages efficiently. Unfortunately for them, those guidelines have leaked and this allows someone abusing the US mail as an illicit distribution channel to evade the USP's checks.</p>

<h2>Suspicious Post Guidelines</h2>

<p>The actual <a href="http://teknopolitik.tumblr.com/post/48178417204/fbi-law-enforcement-bulletin-via-findarticles">guidelines for suspicious packages</a> list a number of major indicators that the inspectors look for. This guide is somewhat outdated, and a <a href="http://www.orlandocriminaldefenseattorneyblog.com/2012/05/drug-trafficking-via-express-m.html">revised version</a> has also be leaked. In both cases, the <strong>triggers</strong> and the reasoning behind them are similar.</p>

<h3>FBI Profiling Criteria</h3>

<ol>
<li>Heavy taping along the seams;</li>
<li>poor preparation for mailing;</li>
<li>uneven weight distribution;</li>
<li>apparent package reuse; and</li>
<li>labels that are handwritten, contain misspellings, originate from a drug-source State, indicate person-to-person not business-to-individual mail, have a return zip code that does not match the accepting post office zip code, a fictitious return address, names of senders or recipients with features in common (John Smith, e.g.) and having no connection to either address</li>
</ol>


<h3>Drug Mail Profile</h3>

<ol>
<li>the use of Express Mail,

<ul>
<li>Express Mail is primarily used by businesses for document delivery.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the weight of the package,

<ul>
<li>drug traffickers are mailing approximately one kilo of cocaine per package, plus some dummy weights</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the package is sent from Puerto Rico, a known drug source location,</li>
<li>the package was mailed from a post office address outside of the zip code on the return address,</li>
<li>an Accurint check reveals that no one by the sender's name lived at the return address,

<ul>
<li>Police will also check Google and Facebook to get more information</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the package is heavily taped at all seams

<ul>
<li>heavy taping may or may not help evade detection by drug sniffing dogs--but we know one thing for sure--it certainly helps draw police attention to the package!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the label is handwritten

<ul>
<li>Since most Express Mail is business-to-business, or business-to-client, labels that aren't typed are suspect</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<h3>Collated</h3>

<p>Anything that looks like someone is sending slightly over an even metric weight of <em>something</em>, from a known suspect location, to another person, in an old heavily taped package with a fake return address. Sounds like bad tradecraft.</p>

<ol>
<li>Suspicious packaging

<ul>
<li>Heavy taping</li>
<li>Package reuse</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Not business mail

<ul>
<li>No printed label</li>
<li>Clearly not documents</li>
<li>Individual to individual</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Known suspicious origin

<ul>
<li>Occasionally specific post offices</li>
<li>Specific countries (Puerto Rico)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Flimsy "return address" cover

<ul>
<li>Fake name</li>
<li>Mismatched name + address</li>
<li>Mismatched address + zipcode</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>Main points to take away:</p>

<ul>
<li>drug packages appear different from normal mail</li>
<li>many factors are contribute to creating a plausible cover/alias.</li>
<li>The packaging of a drug shipment provides a cover, which needs to be backstopped.</li>
</ul>


<p>Don't make shit up, do your research and steal an identity with a real address.</p>

<h2>Backstop your cover</h2>

<p>When creating a cover, make sure it is as fully fleshed out as possible. This means developing supporting evidence to bolster the validity of the cover. In intelligence lingo, this is called backstopping.</p>

<p>A backstopped cover is one where checks to verify the authenticity of the cover story are verifiable. For example, if the cover story includes a name, there are matching identity documents; if there is an phone number, it connects to someone who will substantiate the cover story; if there is an address, it exists. The old Soviet illegals used to spend years developing their cover and backstopping them. They'd live for a few years in a country they claimed to be immigrating from, so they would have the memories, experience and verifiable evidence that they were from there.</p>

<p>If you are going to use a cover (you probably should), then put in the effort to create a backstop. The complexity and depth of that backstop are dependant on how deeply the cover will be investigated. Remember though, it is better to have too much, than not enough...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drug Delivery Service OPSEC]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/drug-delivery-service-opsec/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T06:41:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/drug-delivery-service-opsec</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting lessons on how a modern New York City drug delivery service
uses basic tradecraft to create a reasonable security posture.</p>

<h2>The Source</h2>

<p>This <a href="http://www.vice.com/read/confessions-of-a-drug-dealers-delivery-service-guy">Vice article</a>
provides the source of the information for this blog post. Using some
basic background knowledge on how covert groups operate, it is simple to parse
and analyze the drug delivery service tradecraft.</p>

<h2>Recruitment</h2>

<blockquote><p>a friend of mine solicited hardcore drugs for a Manhattan drug kingpin, who was looking for a new pot delivery guy. My friend encouraged me to try out for the job.</p></blockquote>

<p>As with many covert groups, the recruitment process relied on personal connections.
This <strong>social network</strong> grounded approach to expanding a covert organisation
is generally good for initial security. The recruits are unlikely to be agents
sent to infiltrate the organistation as the long standing social ties between
members and recruits both establishes trust and serves as <strong>vetting</strong>.</p>

<p>Developing a covert organisation based on <strong>social network</strong> ties provides a
means of rapid expansion and easy security clearance. The downside is that once
a single member of the organisation is compromised, the adversarial security forces
can easily roll up the whole network. The poor compartmentation of a <strong>social network</strong>
based covert organisation is its Achilles heel. The security of the organisation
is critically dependent on the security of each individual member.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> Expand your covert network with individuals who are passionate about
your ideological beliefs. Ensure strong compartmentation, starting with recruitment.</p>

<h2>Leverage</h2>

<blockquote><p>He asked me to provide documentation of my current address and phone number as an insurance policy. If I ran out on him, he warned me he’d hold my friends responsible for the deficit funds and/or drugs.</p></blockquote>

<p>The principal of the organisation "Nathan" requires that the recruit provide
a verifiable address and means of contact, along with dire warnings of consequences
in the case of infractions. This is very basic control principles, typical of
covert organisations.</p>

<p>The major security problem with this approach, of course, is that the records
maintained by the network's principal are a high value target for the adversary.
Compromise of the principal's records will lead to total collapse of the network,
and interdiction for every member involved. There is no chance of evasion.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> No logs, no crime. Do not keep records of the members of your covert
organisation. These records are extremely sensitive.</p>

<h2>Operational Actions</h2>

<blockquote><p> the transaction and exit should be as swift as possible. “You aren't here to hang out,” she said. “It's not a social call, and they aren't your friends. You want to walk in and be friendly and make conversation but also get to the business at hand and get out of there quickly.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The illicit operation, the drug sale, is intended to be rapid and minimize
the period of vulnerability for both parties. Interestingly, this is possibly a
poor choice if the threat is surveillance. There are few reasons a random individual
would enter a domicile for a short duration. Also of note, the covert organisation
provides no reasonable cover story for why the agent (the drug courier) is entering
the residence of the client. A simple "what were you doing?" type question would
likely completely blow the whole operation.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> Minimising the period of vulnerability improves the chances of operational
success. Always make sure your agents are capable of delivering plausible cover
stories. <strong>Cover for action</strong></p>

<h2>Cover for Status</h2>

<blockquote><p>Nathan forced me to wear a button-up shirt and slacks, shave my face, and keep my hair conservatively short. He believed this uniform would attract little attention as I walked around with thousands of dollars worth of pot in a laptop case slung over my shoulder.</p></blockquote>

<p>The covert organisation has, surprisingly enough, chosen to enforce a uniform
that makes their agents blend in with the mainstream. This is completely inline
with the typical operational disguises employed by covert organistations operating
in controlled territory the world over. (See: Moscow Rules <code>go with the flow</code>;
Murphy's Laws of War: <code>don't stand out, it draws fire</code>)</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> They got this one exactly right.</p>

<h2>All phones are bugged</h2>

<blockquote><p>Although I used my flip-phone constantly at work, I was never given clients' addresses over the phone. Clients calls would go to a dispatcher—a third party who took the call, traced the number through a database of numbers, and then returned the call from a different phone to confirm their request for drugs. After their request was confirmed, I received a call from another phone. The dispatcher only told me, “You got Nick,” or “You got Lucy.” I was banned from responding with anything besides a murmured “OK.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Each operational use of the phone provides the adversary with minimal value.
There is a unique identifier for the client (e.g. "Lucy"), and the agent
acknowledges receipt of the directive ("OK"). The dispatchers interaction
with the client is itself run over multiple phone lines and kept to short,
simple, normal statements.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> This is very much inline with all covert organisations'
guidelines for using phones. Never use keywords, keep the content as vague as possible,
minimize the period of vulnerability -- get off the phone!</p>

<h2>OPSEC FAIL: attracting attention</h2>

<blockquote><p>Each day I was given a stipend of $40 for cabs. No one knew if I didn’t spend the $40. Instead of taking cabs, I ran around in a frantic state that negated every other measure I took to not draw unwanted attention</p></blockquote>

<p>This is an instance of <strong>preference divergence</strong>, a common problem for covert
organisations. The financial resources provided to the agent of the principal
are siphoned off and directed towards non-operational uses (the drug courier
skims and pockets his cab stipend.) There doesn't appear to be any consequence
to this operational security failure, however it jeopardizes the entire organisation.
If "Nathan" were a more disciplined principal he would monitor his agents more
closely and ensure they are conforming to the organisational security requirements.
Strangely, drug dealers are not strict disciplinarians.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> if the securit of the entire organisation is dependent on the security
of each individual agent -- enforce the operational security requirements strictly!</p>

<h2>Aliases</h2>

<blockquote><p> I shook his hand and said, “I'm Jack.” He gave me a knowing grin. “So that's the name you're using?” he asked.</p></blockquote>

<p>The agent is using an alias to provide pseudonymity from malicious clients. This
provides some minimal level of security. It is definitely better than not having
any cover at all. However, as noted above, it should be combined with a robust
cover story for why the agent is visiting a residential home for a brief period.</p>

<h2>Discharging the agent</h2>

<p>After a promotion, the drug courier decides to find a new line of work. If the
organisation was stricter in their OPSEC practices, the departure of an agent
wouldn't place anyone else in jeopardy. As it stands, it seems clear that the
agent who is now drawing attention to himself by writing about his experience
in a national magazine(!) still retains sufficiently sensitive information to
unravel the network.</p>

<p><strong>ProTip:</strong> compartment early, compartment often. It is safer than any alternative.</p>

<h2>TL;DR</h2>

<p>Compartment your covert organisation from recruitment through to operational
action so that when your agents leave or are compromised they are unable
to compromise the organisation. Ensure that your operational activities have
good <strong>cover for status</strong> (e.g. a disguise) and <strong>cover for action</strong> (e.g. a strong cover story).
Strong compartmentation, strong cover, and be aware of the risks of using social networks
for building a covert organisation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
