<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PORTAL | Hacker OPSEC]]></title>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/categories/portal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-11T02:41:36+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://grugq.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[the grugq]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[the.grugq@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thru a PORTAL Darkly]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/05/thru-a-portal-darkly/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-05T15:08:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/05/thru-a-portal-darkly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The Design and Implementation of P.O.R.T.A.L</h2>

<p>The <strong>P</strong>ersonal <strong>O</strong>nion <strong>R</strong>outer <strong>T</strong>o <strong>A</strong>ssure <strong>L</strong>iberty is designed
to protect the user by isolating their computer behind a router that forces all
traffic over the Tor network.</p>

<h2>PORTAL Gooooooooooooooaaaaaaaaaaals!!!!!!</h2>

<p>The goal of the PORTAL project is to create a compartmented network segment
that can <strong>only</strong> send data to the Tor network. To accomplish this the PORTAL
device itself is physically isolated and locked down to prevent malicious
tampering originating from the protected network. So if the user's computer is
compromised by malware, the malware is unable to modify the Tor software or
configuration, nor can it directly access the Internet (completely
preventing IP address leakage). Additionally, the PORTAL is configured to fail
close -- if the connection to Tor drops, the user loses their Internet access.
Finally, the PORTAL is "idiot proof", simply turn it on and it works.</p>

<h2>The Implementation, the Pain, the Horror</h2>

<p>The initial requirement was to develop PORTAL for a small personal sized router,
such as the TP-Link 703N, 3040, or M1U. All of these devices are small, portable
and support the OpenWRT open source router firmware. Unfortunately, it turns out
that "small" and "portable" is synonymous with "weak" and "underpowered".</p>

<p>Unfortunately, Tor is quite resource intensive for an embedded device. Tor uses 16MB of RAM
and for complete functionality (requiring the GeoIP database) it occupies slightly
over 1.2MB of <code>squashfs</code> space. The stock TP-LINK routers have only 4MB of flash
and 16MB of RAM (later models have increased RAM). This caused a lot of problems
when building early versions. A bare bones OpenWRT system stripped down to just
support an Internet uplink USB device occupies 3.2MB of <code>squashfs</code> space. Using
the power of math we see: <code>3.2 + 1.2 &gt; 4.0</code>. Fuck.</p>

<h3>Enter The Dragon, or Chinese Hackers to the Rescue</h3>

<p>Fortunately, the TP-LINK routers are not just small, they are also extremely hackable. They are very popular
with hackers who have modified the hardware and expanded the capabilities of the
stock device. I got in contact with a Chinese hacker who has upgraded the
TP-LINK 703N to 16MB of flash and 64MB of RAM. Sweet. Using these modified routers
development of the PORTAL became much much easier.</p>

<h2>PORTAL System Architecture</h2>

<p>The PORTAL requires a minimum of two network interfaces: one for the Internet
uplink, and one for the isolated network segment. In order to protect the PORTAL from
tampering from malware (or malicious users), it also requires a third administration
interface. This can be either a serial console, or physical connection. The reason
not to use WiFi for the administration network is that that would expose the
administration interface to anyone within WiFi range, including potentially the
user's compromised laptop's WiFi card.</p>

<h3>Three Interfaces to Rule Them All</h3>

<p>The requirement to protect the PORTAL from a malicious user caused some problems
since the device hardware has very limited interfaces. The TP-LINK 703N has only:</p>

<pre><code>* 1 x USB 2.0
* 1 x 100MB ethernet
* 1 x onboard wifi
</code></pre>

<p>All available interfaces are required to get us to the three networks we need:</p>

<pre><code>* Tor: isolated proxy interface
    * Tor SOCKS proxy
    * Tor Transparent TCP proxy
    * Tor Transparent DNS proxy
    * DHCP (optional)
* Admin: configuration management interface
    * ssh
    * https (optional)
    * DHCP (optional)
* Internet: uplink connection interface
    * No services
</code></pre>

<h2>Operational PORTAL</h2>

<p>After the user has configured the <code>Internet</code>, and whatever other adjustments they
wish to make, they shouldn't need to connect to the <code>Admin</code> interface again. This
leaves us with a very hard target for any attacker who wishes to unmask us
(modulo any issues with Tor itself).</p>

<p>The PORTAL has been hardened to make it significantly more difficult for the user
to make a mistake, or for an attacker to subvert the Tor protections. From the
<code>Tor</code> network the only exposed ports are Tor's DNS proxy, TCP proxy, and SOCKS.
Optionally, you can use DHCP on this network.</p>

<p>If, somehow, the firewall doesn't work properly, you're still safe because the
PORTAL doesn't actually route packets. The <em>only</em> way you can reach the Internet
(regardless of which interface you're connected to) is via Tor. This stops stupid
mistakes, such as connecting to the <code>Admin</code> interface and forgetting to swap to
the <code>Tor</code> network. Don't worry, you can't do that, it won't work, you're welcome.</p>

<p>Final hardening is left up to the user who will have to assign the <code>Admin</code> and
<code>Tor</code> networks to physical interfaces. There are security trade offs either way.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Medium Security:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Tor</code> = WiFi</li>
<li><code>Admin</code> = Ethernet</li>
<li>pros: ease of use</li>
<li>cons: pre-Tor plaintext will be broadcast over the AEther (see: Hammond)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Maximum Security:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Tor</code> = Ethernet</li>
<li><code>Admin</code> = WiFi</li>
<li>pros: ultra secure</li>
<li>cons: if an attacker cracks your WPA2 PSK, they'll have access to your
    management sshd. Of course, they'll be so physically close to you
    at that point, leaking your IP is the least of your worries.</li>
<li><strong>NOTE:</strong> remove the WiFi card from your computer to block access via
      malware compromise</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Just Do It</h2>

<p>The PORTAL project has been migrated to the RaspberryPi, which has more power
to support Tor. It requires more configuration, which is something I'll work on,
however the ease of acquisition of the RPi makes this the current platform of
choice. So go install <a href="http://github.com/grugq/PORTALofPi">PORTAL of Pi</a> and
compartment all of your sensitive operational activities inside an isolated Tor network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
