<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Silk Road | Hacker OPSEC]]></title>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/categories/silk-road/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://grugq.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-06T06:52:47+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://grugq.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[the grugq]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[the.grugq@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Silk Road Security]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/silk-road-security/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T18:53:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/silk-road-security</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Counterintelligence Lessons for Drug Dealers</h2>

<p><strong>NOTE</strong> Events have overtaken my slow writing speed. This post was in the works
before the Silk Road bust in September 2013. I'm uploading it anyway because it
has some useful information, however there seems little point in finish it now.</p>

<p>The dealers on Silk Road ship a large amount of illegal products around the world, and it is clear that they're successful at it. However, the US Postal service has been aware that drug dealers user their service for shipping illegal substances and has developed guidelines for determining suspect packages efficiently. Unfortunately for them, those guidelines have leaked and this allows someone abusing the US mail as an illicit distribution channel to evade the USP's checks.</p>

<h2>Suspicious Post Guidelines</h2>

<p>The actual <a href="http://teknopolitik.tumblr.com/post/48178417204/fbi-law-enforcement-bulletin-via-findarticles">guidelines for suspicious packages</a> list a number of major indicators that the inspectors look for. This guide is somewhat outdated, and a <a href="http://www.orlandocriminaldefenseattorneyblog.com/2012/05/drug-trafficking-via-express-m.html">revised version</a> has also be leaked. In both cases, the <strong>triggers</strong> and the reasoning behind them are similar.</p>

<h3>FBI Profiling Criteria</h3>

<ol>
<li>Heavy taping along the seams;</li>
<li>poor preparation for mailing;</li>
<li>uneven weight distribution;</li>
<li>apparent package reuse; and</li>
<li>labels that are handwritten, contain misspellings, originate from a drug-source State, indicate person-to-person not business-to-individual mail, have a return zip code that does not match the accepting post office zip code, a fictitious return address, names of senders or recipients with features in common (John Smith, e.g.) and having no connection to either address</li>
</ol>


<h3>Drug Mail Profile</h3>

<ol>
<li>the use of Express Mail,

<ul>
<li>Express Mail is primarily used by businesses for document delivery.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the weight of the package,

<ul>
<li>drug traffickers are mailing approximately one kilo of cocaine per package, plus some dummy weights</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the package is sent from Puerto Rico, a known drug source location,</li>
<li>the package was mailed from a post office address outside of the zip code on the return address,</li>
<li>an Accurint check reveals that no one by the sender's name lived at the return address,

<ul>
<li>Police will also check Google and Facebook to get more information</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the package is heavily taped at all seams

<ul>
<li>heavy taping may or may not help evade detection by drug sniffing dogs--but we know one thing for sure--it certainly helps draw police attention to the package!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the label is handwritten

<ul>
<li>Since most Express Mail is business-to-business, or business-to-client, labels that aren't typed are suspect</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<h3>Collated</h3>

<p>Anything that looks like someone is sending slightly over an even metric weight of <em>something</em>, from a known suspect location, to another person, in an old heavily taped package with a fake return address. Sounds like bad tradecraft.</p>

<ol>
<li>Suspicious packaging

<ul>
<li>Heavy taping</li>
<li>Package reuse</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Not business mail

<ul>
<li>No printed label</li>
<li>Clearly not documents</li>
<li>Individual to individual</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Known suspicious origin

<ul>
<li>Occasionally specific post offices</li>
<li>Specific countries (Puerto Rico)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Flimsy "return address" cover

<ul>
<li>Fake name</li>
<li>Mismatched name + address</li>
<li>Mismatched address + zipcode</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>Main points to take away:</p>

<ul>
<li>drug packages appear different from normal mail</li>
<li>many factors are contribute to creating a plausible cover/alias.</li>
<li>The packaging of a drug shipment provides a cover, which needs to be backstopped.</li>
</ul>


<p>Don't make shit up, do your research and steal an identity with a real address.</p>

<h2>Backstop your cover</h2>

<p>When creating a cover, make sure it is as fully fleshed out as possible. This means developing supporting evidence to bolster the validity of the cover. In intelligence lingo, this is called backstopping.</p>

<p>A backstopped cover is one where checks to verify the authenticity of the cover story are verifiable. For example, if the cover story includes a name, there are matching identity documents; if there is an phone number, it connects to someone who will substantiate the cover story; if there is an address, it exists. The old Soviet illegals used to spend years developing their cover and backstopping them. They'd live for a few years in a country they claimed to be immigrating from, so they would have the memories, experience and verifiable evidence that they were from there.</p>

<p>If you are going to use a cover (you probably should), then put in the effort to create a backstop. The complexity and depth of that backstop are dependant on how deeply the cover will be investigated. Remember though, it is better to have too much, than not enough...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It was DPR, in the Tor HS, with the BTC]]></title>
    <link href="http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/it-was-dpr/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T19:44:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://grugq.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/it-was-dpr</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Give it to me straight, dr the grugq</h2>

<p>Generally, it appears that Ross Ulbricht was applying his economic and
techno-libertarian philosophy to real life. As his project grew, his security
posture improved -- too late. The most serious mistakes that Ross Ulbricht made
were made during the period Jan 2011 - Oct 2011. A full timeline of the events
in the Complaint is available on <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/62914009002/silk-road-investigation-timeline">my tumblr</a>.</p>

<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> This is an abridged version of a longer post pulling out the lessons learned
from the <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/62909883417/ulricht-indictment-aka-dread-pirate-roberts-aka-silk">Silk Road Complaint</a> of 27th September 2013. This post will only list the OPSEC errors,
rather than explore them in detail.</p>

<h2>The OPSEC Failures</h2>

<p>The fundamental error is poor compartmentation. Ross Ulbricht, the real person
and the online persona (Google+, LinkedIn, etc), and the Dread Pirate Roberts
persona share ideological views and geographic locations. There is contamination
between the two personas. Most of these seem to be due to the organic evolution
of the Silk Road venture, where early naive Ulbricht makes mistakes that later
smarter DPR wouldn't. Unfortunately, the later DPR is more ideologically
extreme and consequently less savvy about mainstream society.</p>

<ol>
<li>Poor Compartmentation</li>
<li>Profiling</li>
<li>Geographic Location</li>
<li>Isolation</li>
</ol>


<h3>Poor Compartmentation</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Contamination</strong>: seriously fatal links created between personas

<ul>
<li><strong>Silk Road</strong> + <strong>altoid</strong>: Shroomery, BitcoinTalk forums</li>
<li><strong>altoid</strong> + <strong>rossulbricht@gmail.com</strong>: BitcoinTalk</li>
<li><strong>Ross Ulbricht</strong> + <strong>frosty@frosty[.com]</strong>: StackOverflow</li>
<li><strong>frosty@frosty</strong> + <strong>Silk Road</strong>: Silk Road server admin SSH key</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>The compartmentation failures are somewhat pervasive, in particular the ideological
"Austrian School of Economics" and the mises.org site. However two particular
contamination errors stand out:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Silk Road</strong> --> <strong>altoid</strong> --> <strong>rossulbricht@gmail.com</strong> link in 2011</li>
<li><strong>Ross Ulbricht</strong> --> <strong>frosty@frosty.com</strong> --> <strong>Silk Road</strong> server link in 2013</li>
</ol>


<p>The first of these failures happened because the <strong>altoid</strong> persona used to
promoted <strong>Silk Road</strong> was poorly fleshed out (e.g. no email address). Ross did not
put the plumbing in place to backstop his <strong>altoid</strong> cover. He then joined the
BitcoinTalk community using this contaminated cover. His participation and search
for social validation left him with his guard down. Consequently, he revealed a
great deal of profiling information about his project and beliefs. Many of his
posts are about Silk Road infrastructure or his mises.org influenced economic
theories. After participating for 10 months he finally made the
<strong>fatal OPSEC error</strong> of posting his personal email address.</p>

<p>The second error was poor compartmentation of his online Ross Ulbricht persona,
the tech savvy San Francisco based startup guy, and "frosty" the system admin
of the server hosting the Silk Road site. His poor compartmentation, likely
using the same computer for both personal and business use, and his
limited backstopping of the DPR/altoid/frosty persona meant that any error would be
fatal.</p>

<p>These two errors combine to link Silk Road with Ross Ulbricht, and Ross Ulbricht
with Silk Road.</p>

<h3>"I'll take Profiles for $300, Alex" : "Too much in common" : "What do Ulbricht and DPR share?"</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Profiling</strong>: Ross Ulbricht talks and acts like Dread Pirate Roberts

<ul>
<li>LinkedIn profile</li>
<li>Timezone leakage: private messages, <a href="http://media.encrypted.cc/files/dpr_posts_pdt.png">forum posting times</a></li>
<li>BitcoinTalk <strong>altoid</strong> <a href="http://grugq.tumblr.com/post/62919678278/osint-case-study-ross-ulbricht-aka-dread-pirate">posts about</a>: economics (mises.org), security, programming</li>
<li>Silk Road Forum <strong>Dread Pirate Roberts</strong> -> Mises + "Austrian School of Economics"</li>
<li>Mises.org <strong>Ross Ulbricht</strong> account</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Ross Ulbricht, the person, was an active participant in the mises.org website
and the BitcoinTalk forums. In both cases he was deeply committed to the
"Austrian School of Economics", something the Dread Pirate Roberts was also a
huge fan of. The <strong>altoid</strong> cover alias, linked directly to Ross Ulbricht,
frequently talked about bitcoin security and PHP programming. He is, based on
his posts, clearly invovled in running some sort of PHP based bitcoin using
venture that requires high security. Sort of like the <strong>Silk Road</strong> site.</p>

<ul>
<li>Geographic Location

<ul>
<li>Silk Road web server administered over VPN from a server</li>
<li>VPN server IP stored in the Silk Road PHP source code</li>
<li>VPN server accessed from a location <code>15240 cm</code> (<code>500 ft</code>) from a location that accessed the Ross Ulbricht GMail account.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>The location of the Dread Pirate Roberts was something of an open secret. It is
clear that he was based in the west coast of the US. Ulbricht was located
in San Francisco at the same time as DPR, as proved by his large online
footprint: Google+, YouTube, GMail.</p>

<h2>Isolation is bad, mmmkay</h2>

<ul>
<li>Isolation without relief

<ul>
<li>Rented room under assumed name</li>
<li>No "mainstream" social circle to realign with social mores</li>
<li>No peers to talk to, only Silk Road forum members and admins</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>After the <strong>altoid</strong> persona is retired from BitcoinTalk, Ulbricht migrates
his social interaction to a more extreme community: the Silk Road forums. This
appears to have been his "scene", where he interacted with people and
cultivated friends (including an impressive array of undercover law
enforcement officials).</p>

<p>The underground life forced on Ulbricht as the Dread Pirate Roberts led to
the major problem of isolation. Human beings are social animals. We require
social interaction to maintain a healthy mental state. The strict
security of DPR required isolation, leaving Ross Ulbricht living his social
life on forums with niche ideological views, initially BitcointTalk (in 2011)
and then the Silk Road forums. Isolation from mainstream society is known to
lead to ideological extremism as members of the niche community self-reinforce
their ideological tendencies. Consequently, they are less able to understand
mainstream society's ideas, beliefs and morals. This is dangerous. This
isolation leads him to rationalize hiring online hitmen to preserve the
Silk Road community is morally acceptable.</p>

<p>Apparently the only source of social validation and ego gratification that Ross
had was a group of bitcoin libertarians, drug seekers, drug dealers and undercover
cops. This is not a healthy social environment conducive to a balanced state of
mental health.</p>

<h2>What have we learned?</h2>

<p>So, the Dread Pirate Roberts Complaint basically tells us nothing that we didn't
already <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/grugq/opsec-for-hackers">know about OPSEC</a>.
There are some lessons learned which can be used to harden OPSEC practices going
forward. The main things are still: strong compartmentation; use Tor
all the time; avoid leaking profiling information, and it is prudent to
regularly migrate to new cover personas.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
